When I was 11,
عندما كنت في الحادية عشره ..
I remember waking up one morning to the sound of joy in my house.
أتذكر أني استيقظت على حس السعاده في أحد الأيام
My father was listening to BBC News
أبي كان يستمع إلى إذاعة الـBBC
on his small, gray radio.
على جهازه الراديو الرمادي الصغير
There was a big smile on his face which was unusual then,
كانت هناك ابتسامه كبيره تعتلي محياه .. والتي كانت نادره في ذلك الوقت ..
because the news mostly depressed him.
لأن الأخبار كانت تحبطه بالعاده
"The Taliban are gone!" my father shouted.
" طالبـــــــــان رحــــــــــــــــلوا " صرخ أبي
I didn't know what it meant,
لم أكن أعرف ما الذي يعنيه !
but I could see that my father was very, very happy.
لكني كنت أستطيع أن أدرك أن والدي كان سعيد جداً جداً
"You can go to a real school now," he said.
قال والدي : ( تستطيعين الذهاب إلى مدرسه حقيقه الآن )
A morning that I will never forget.
صباح لن أنساه أبدا
A real school.
مدرسه حقيقيه !!
You see, I was six when the Taliban took over Afghanistan
لاحظوا .. لقد كنت في السادسه عندما استولت طالبان على أفغانستان
and made it illegal for girls to go to school.
وجعلت تعليم الفتيات غير قانوني
So for the next five years, I dressed as a boy
لذا في الخمس سنوات التالية لإحتلال طالبان لأفغانستان ، كنت ألبس كالأولاد
to escort my older sister, who was no longer allowed
لمرافقة أختي الكبيره التي لم يعد يسمح لها
to be outside alone, to a secret school.
بالخروج وحدها ،كنت أرافقها لمدرسه سريه
It was the only way we both could be educated.
كانت تلك الطريقه الوحيده التي تمكننا نحن الإثنتان من الحصول على التعليم
Each day, we took a different route
كل يوم ، نأخذ طريقاً مختلفا
so that no one would suspect where we were going.
لكي لا يشك أحد بأين نحن ذاهبون
We would cover our books in grocery bags
كنا نغطي كتبنا في أكياس البقاله
so it would seem we were just out shopping.
لكي نظهر وكأننا ذاهبين للتسوق
The school was in a house,
المدرسه كانت في بيت
more than 100 of us packed in one small living room.
أكثر من 100 شخص كانوا ينحشرون في غرفة معيشه
It was cozy in winter but extremely hot in summer.
كان البيت دافئا في البرد لكنه حار جدا في الصيف
We all knew we were risking our lives --
كلنا كنا نعلم أننا نخاطر بحياتنا
the teacher, the students and our parents.
المعلمين والطلاب وكذلك آبائنا
From time to time, the school would suddenly be canceled
من وقت لآخر كانت تلغى المدرسة فجأة
for a week because Taliban were suspicious.
لأسبوع لأن طالبان بدأت تشك
We always wondered what they knew about us.
كنا دائما نتسائل ! ماذا يعرفون عنا ؟
Were we being followed?
لماذا يتم ملاحقتنا ؟
Do they know where we live?
هل يعرفون أين نعيش ؟
We were scared,
كنا خائــفين
but still, school was where we wanted to be.
لكن بالرغم من ذلك المدرسه هي المكان الذي نريد أن نكون فيه
I was very lucky to grow up in a family
كنت محظوظه جدا لأنشأ في عائله تقدر التعليم وتعتز بالفتيات
My grandfather was an extraordinary man for his time.
جدي كان رجل استثنائي في وقته
A total maverick from a remote province of Afghanistan,
إستقل من ولاية بعيده في أفغانستان
he insisted that his daughter, my mom,
أصر على أن تذهب ابنته ، ( أمي )
go to school, and for that he was disowned by his father.
إلى المدرسه ، ولهذا السبب تبرأ منه والده
But my educated mother became a teacher.
لكن أمي المتعلمة أصبحت أستاذة
There she is.
ها هي
She retired two years ago, only to turn our house
تقاعدت أمي قبل سنتين، لتحول منزلنا
into a school for girls and women in our neighborhood.
إلى مدرسه لفتيات ونساء حيِنا
And my father -- that's him --
ووالدي ، -- هذا هو --
he was the first ever in his family to receive an education.
كان أول شخص يحصل على التعليم في عائلته
There was no question that his children
لم يكن هناك شك في أن أبنائه سيحصلون على التعليم بما في ذلك بناته
would receive an education, including his daughters,
لم يكن هناك شك في أن أبنائه سيحصلون على التعليم، بما في ذلك بناته
despite the Taliban, despite the risks.
على الرغم من طالبان ، وعلى الرغم من كل المخاطر
To him, there was greater risk in not educating his children.
بالنسبه له ، كانت هناك خطوره أكبر في أن يترك أطفاله بدون تعليم
During Taliban years, I remember
خلال سنوات طالبان
there were times I would get so frustrated by our life
كانت هناك أوقات يخيب فيها أملي من حياتنا وأصاب بالإحباط
and always being scared and not seeing a future.
ودائما ما أكون خائفه ولا أرى المستقبل
I would want to quit,
أريد أن أتوقف
but my father,
لكن والدي
he would say,
كان يقول :
"Listen, my daughter,
اصغي يا ابنتي
you can lose everything you own in your life.
تستطيعين أن تخسرين كل شيء في حياتك
Your money can be stolen. You can be forced to leave your home during a war.
نقودك من الممكن أن تسرقين، من الممكن أن تُجبرين على ترك وطنك في الحرب
But the one thing that will always remain with you
لكن الشيء الذي يبقى دائـــــما معك
is what is here,
ما هو موجود هنا
and if we have to sell our blood to pay your school fees,
فإذا كنا مضطرين لبيع دمنا حتى ندفع رسوم المدرسه
we will.
فسنفعل
So do you still not want to continue?"
فهل أنت مصره على عدم الإستمرار ؟
Today I am 22.
اليوم عمري 22 عاماً
I was raised in a country that has been destroyed
ولقد نشأت في بلد دمرته عقود من الحرب
Fewer than six percent of women my age have made it beyond high school,
أقل من 6% من النساء في عمري ذهبوا إلى مرحله أبعد من الثانويه
and had my family not been so committed to my education,
بالإضافه إلى ذلك لولا أن عائلتي لم تكن تفرض علي التعليم
I would be one of them.
لكنت واحده من مَنهم
Instead, I stand here a proud graduate of Middlebury College.
بدلا ما ذلك، أقف هنا وأنا فخوره بتخرجي من كلية Middlebury
(Applause)
تصفيق
When I returned to Afghanistan, my grandfather,
عندما عدت إلى أفغانستان، جدي
the one exiled from his home for daring to educate his daughters,
جدي الذي اغترب عن منزله ليعلم بناته بكل ثقه
was among the first to congratulate me.
كان أول الأشخاص الذين هنئوني
He not only brags about my college degree,
هو لا يتفاخر حول شهادتي الجامعيه فقط
but also that I was the first woman,
لكن يفخر أيضا بأنني كنت أول إمرأة
and that I am the first woman
وأنا أول إمرأة
to drive him through the streets of Kabul.
أقود به عبر شوارع كابول
(Applause)
تصفيق
My family believes in me.
عائلتي تؤمن بي
I dream big, but my family dreams even bigger for me.
أحلامي كبيره ، لكن عائلتي ترسم أحلام أكبر لي
That's why I am a global ambassador for 10x10,
ولهذا السبب أنا سفيره عالميه لمنظمة 10×10
a global campaign to educate women.
وهي حمله عالميه لتعليم النساء
That's why I cofounded SOLA,
ولهذا السبب أيضا كنت شريكة بتأسيس SOLA
the first and perhaps only boarding school
أول مدرسة وربما المدرسة الداخلية الأولى للفتيات في أفغانستان
a country where it's still risky for girls to go to school.
الدوله التي لا يزال من الخطر على الفتيات الذهاب إلى المدرسة
The exciting thing is that I see students at my school
الشيء المثير هو أني أرى الطلاب في مدرستي ينتهزون الفرص بطموح
And I see their parents and their fathers
وأرى والديهم وآبائهم
who, like my own, advocate for them,
مثل أبي، يؤيدونهم
despite and even in the face of daunting opposition.
بالرغم من كل المواجهات الشاقة
Like Ahmed. That's not his real name,
مثل أحمد ، هذا ليس اسمه الحقيقي
and I cannot show you his face,
ولا أستطيع أن أريكم وجهه
but Ahmed is the father of one of my students.
لكن أحمد هو أب لأحد طالباتي
Less than a month ago, he and his daughter
قبل أقل من شهرمضى، هو و ابنته كانو في طريقهم من مدرسة SOLA إلى قريتهم
were on their way from SOLA to their village,
كانوا في طريقهم من مدرسة SOLA إلى قريتهم
and they literally missed being killed
وهم حـرفيا نجوا من فرصة موت محققة
by a roadside bomb by minutes.
جائت عن طريق انفجار عبوة ناسفة في دقيقة
As he arrived home, the phone rang,
لحظة وصوله المنزل، رن الهاتف،
a voice warning him
صوت يحذره،
that if he sent his daughter back to school,
إذا أرسل إبنته مرة أخرى إلى المدرسة
they would try again.
سوف يحاولون مرة أخرى
"Kill me now, if you wish," he said,
" أقتلني الآن إذا كنت تريد ذلك " قال ذلك
"but I will not ruin my daughter's future
"لكني لن أدمر مستقبل إبنتي
because of your old and backward ideas."
بسبب أفكارك القديمة والمتخلفة"
What I've come to realize about Afghanistan,
الشيء الذي أصبحت أدركه عن أفغانستان
and this is something that is often dismissed in the West,
وهذا الشيء غالبا ما يتم رفضه في الغرب
that behind most of us who succeed
أن وراء معظم الناجحين منا
is a father who recognizes the value in his daughter
أب أدرك قيمة ابنته
and who sees that her success is his success.
والذي يرى نجاحها من نجاحُه هو
It's not to say that our mothers aren't key in our success.
هذا لا يعني أن أمهاتنا ليسوا رموز في نجاحاتنا
In fact, they're often the initial and convincing negotiators
في الحقيقة في كثير من الأحيان يكونون هم المفاوضين المقنعين
of a bright future for their daughters,
الأوائل لمستقبل مشرق لفتياتهم
but in the context of a society like in Afghanistan,
لكن في مجتمع مثل أفغانستان
we must have the support of men.
يجب أن يكون لدينا دعم من الرجال
Under the Taliban, girls who went to school
تحت حكم طالبان، الفتيات الذين يذهبون إلى المدرسة
numbered in the hundreds --
يحصون بالمئات
remember, it was illegal.
تذكروا ، كانت دراسة الفتيات غير قانونية
But today, more than three million girls are in school in Afghanistan.
لكن اليوم ، أكثر من ثلاثة ملايين فتاة في المدرسة في أفغانستان
(Applause)
تصفيــــــق
Afghanistan looks so different from here in America.
أفغانستان تبدو مختلفه جدا من هنا في أمريكا
I find that Americans see the fragility in changes.
أرى أن الأمريكان يجدون ضعف في التغييرات
I fear that these changes will not last
أخشى أن هذه التغييرات لن تستمر
much beyond the U.S. troops' withdrawal.
بعد انسحاب القوات الأمريكية
But when I am back in Afghanistan,
لكن عندما رجعت إلى أفغانستان
when I see the students in my school
ووجدت الطلاب في مدرستي
and their parents who advocate for them,
وآبائتهم الذين يؤيدونهم
who encourage them, I see a promising future
ويشجعونهم، أرى مستقبلا واعداً
and lasting change.
وتغيير دائم
To me, Afghanistan is a country of hope and boundless possibilities,
بالنسبه لي ، أفغانستان هي موطن الأمل والقدرات الّامحدودة
and every single day
وفي كل يوم الفتيات في SOLA يذكروني بهذا
the girls of SOLA remind me of that.
الفتيات في SOLA يذكروني بهذا
Like me, they are dreaming big.
مثلي ، يحلمون أحلام كبيرة
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
تصفيق